Hi everyone. My name is
Dr. Matthew Heller. I am a
family medicine and sports
medicine physician and an
associate professor at
NYC College of Osteopathic
Medicine. Today I have the
honor of presenting to you
all a very important lecture,
a lecture that hopefully
you're going to remember
throughout your medical
career because it's going
to be very important when
you guys are in the hospital
taking care of patients.
Today's lecture is going to
be about potassium disorder.
Again, my name is Matthew
Heller. Here is my
email address. If anyone
has any questions or
concerns about anything,
please let me know. Last
time I presented to you
all, I still kept the
bird as part of this logo
over here for Twitter.
And as a Snapple fact,
the bird was named Larry,
right? And the bird
was named Larry.
It was named after Larry Bird,
um uh the basketball former
basketball player uh so
we're going to get ahead
with the lecture because we
have a lot to talk about um
so before we go on to the
next slide I want you all
to imagine that the year
is 2027 and we're in the
month of july july 2027
right you are the intern on
call uh you're at the hospital
you graduated medical
school about two months ago
and uh you've been up since
5 a.m. the day before,
right? You've been working
non-stop since 5 a.m.
the day before and you completed
your last ER admission,
right? And you will
finally have a little bit
of time to go to bed to
get two to three hours
before you have to wake up
again for morning rounds.
You put your head on
the pillow and as soon
as you do close your
eyes, the pacer goes off
and the nurse is on the
floor and she wants to notify
you about a critical lab,
right? So two hours into sleep
you get notified critical
lab and they say doc the
patient John Smith has a
potassium level of 6.2 and she
goes is that okay you're
very tired and you would love
nothing more than to just
go right back to bed but
you roll out of bed at a very
fast pace you go evaluate
the person uh the patient uh
you're nervous but you are
prepared because after all
you are a nine-time grad.
You're making your
way to evaluate the
patient and then you
remember Dr. Heller's
lecture when you were
a second year medical
student. You get to
the patient's room,
you evaluate the
patient and you begin
initiating treatment
for the patient and
now you just save
the patient's life.
The next morning you
present the patient
during morning round
to the entire medical
team and the attending
stops you, gives you
a pat on the back and
says job well done.
So all All those
years of hard work
in medical school
makes it worth it.
And you may not see it now
on a day-to-day basis as
a second year medical
student. You don't see this
high or low potassium every
day, you don't see all
these medical conditions
every day, but the hard work
you put in today is
certainly going to be paying
off tomorrow when you guys
are practicing medicine.
Today's session
objective is we're going
to be talking about
potassium. right? We're
going to be talking
about normal versus
abnormal, right? Too
high is not so good.
It's very not good. And
too low can also be very
not good, right? So
you want to have a good
balance of potassium within
the body. We're going
to talk about the diagnosis
and treatment of hypo,
which is low, and hyper,
which is high potassium.
And come up with a
differential diagnosis.
We're going to look at EKG,
right? Not too detailed,
but there's certain EKG
finding we're to be looking for
for a patient that might
have high or low potassium.
And I think the main
thing is we mentioned
before is the treatment.
You're going to want
to initiate treatment
pretty quick once you
realize that a patient
has true hyperkalemia.
So throughout the lecture,
I do incorporate the
cookie model for the treatment
of hyper and hypokalemia.
I hope you all like it.
If you do, please leave
a comment in the evaluation
form for the lecture.
So if you have any
ideas to make it better,
obviously you can always
let me know. And I'm
always trying to make
the lectures better and
more fun as well as
educational for you all.
But today we do
have a very special
guest. It's Ponder the Lecture.
Everybody's favorite
is Cookie Monster.
And we'll talk more
about him later on. Who
are we? We are the Red
Wolves and the Bears.
Um, so hello down in Jungle,
or hello up in New
York, Long Island.
We'll do a quick roll call.
So if you are the, um,
if you are the Bears up north.
And if you're down south,
let me hear you howl.
We'll move on to the lecture.
So before we even get
on, the question always
becomes, what is K? What is K
and how did it evolve as
we go through our lifetime?
So Yogi Berra, great guy,
former Yankees, so his
simple answer would
always be K, just three
simple lines that make up
a K. And that would be a
Yogi Berra type answer.
right? One line, two
line, and three line.
But as we go through life,
K evolved, right? When
we're four to five years
old, right, we're taught
that K stands for kangaroo.
Then we get into
the Little League,
and we begin to play baseball,
and K is not such a great
thing, right? K
means strikeout.
And we get to medical
school, and then
we realize K is
also for potassium.
And then once you get
your first big people job,
right, K becomes your
response to everything,
right, because you always want
to do the right thing, so,
K.
And your text message with the
When you're told
to do something,
your response will be K.
Soap notes, K.
Potassium lecture, K.
Be nice and medical student,
definitely, okay.
But if we try to get a second
opinion on what is K, right?
We ask this guy over
here, what is K?
He's going to say
K is for cookies.
But today's lecture is
not going to have anything
about kangaroo,
baseball, or cookies.
today's lecture will be
strictly about potassium.
And we'll talk about
hyperkalemia and hypokalemia,
right, and how to treat and
how to diagnose both of them.
And we don't want to
have too much and we
don't want to have
too little potassium.
When we first talk about
potassium, right, one
thing we need to always
keep in mind is that
the lab value is only
as good as the specimen
that's provided. And
what does that even mean?
That means that you have
to give a good specimen
that's got to go directly
to the lab once the lab is
drawn, right? So if you
take out blood and you
leave it sitting on the
table while you watch the
bottom of the 13th inning
of the Yankee game, right,
while you're watching the
bottom of the 13th inning
of the Yankee game, right,
the blood is going to go
through a process where
hemolysis, where it's going to
break down, the cells are
going to break down and the
potassium is going to be
falsely elevated. Now you're
going to have a falsely
elevated potassium which is
not going to be a true
potassium so in a sense it's
going to be a pseudo hyperkalemia,
meaning it's going to
be a fake elevated number
that you're going to see.
Location of the drawer,
you want to avoid drawing
from a limb with an IV
and if necessary you might
need to stop the IV 30
minutes and do a venous
blood distal to the IV
site. The key thing here
is we want to decrease
the risk of hemolysis. We
want to decrease that
chance of the cell breaking
down creating a folically
elevated potassium.
You might hear me say
this a few times and it's
very important today or
for this lecture that
potassium is intracellular
and that means that most of
the potassium like to
hang out inside the cell,
right? So anything that's
going to break the cell down
or break apart the cell,
right, is going to fully
elevate or it's going to
elevate the potassium, right?
So later on we talk about burn,
we talk about rhabdomyolysis,
we talk about other
conditions, the cell
breakdown, right, it's going
to raise the potassium level.
There are different
ways to obtain specimen
that will allow us
for, that allows us to
check the electrolytes.
For example, most
commonly, we're going
to try to determine the
lab value through the
venous blood. So think
about your last doctor
visit. You went to
the doctor, they took
some blood from you.
Chance at all, they
probably didn't take it
from an artery. They
probably took it from
the vein. They took it
from the vein, and they're
checking the
electrolytes, and they're
checking any other lab
test that was ordered.
So you get potassium, you
can get it through the
venous, the arterial, and
the urine, and you can also
get a number through the,
well, not a number. But
you can also check the EKG
that might be significant
in cases where patients
have hyper and hypokalemia.
I put this in here.
This has always been
part of my lecture,
and as times evolve,
right, we're becoming
more EMR-based, right,
we're becoming,
everything is becoming
more online. But there
was a time where we
had to write everything
down on paper.
And when we write
everything down on paper,
it was always a pain
to have to write.
Sodium, chloride, bicobs,
potassium, B-urine,
creacinine, just
writing everything out.
So this was a standard
diagram that was always used.
And this might be worth
knowing because you may not
always have the EMR in front
of you or you might have to
quickly evaluate and obtain
information from the EMR
so that you can present to
your attending, to the team,
the medical team, and so
this might save you a little
bit of time right but this
is a standard convention
of how to write the different
electrolytes and the
different lab so I don't want
to spend too much time on
this but if you were to fill
this out you put 138 over
here and basically that 138
meant sodium right because
that's what the sodium value
was right and then you put
the chloride over here the
numbers are applied you
put 100 right then the
potassium was 3.5 so you put 3.5
and this was pretty much a
standard convention how we
write on document lab one
we had to write on paper
but now again everything you
get the lab value everything
goes through the EMR gets
scanned in right but if
you ever need to write it
down on paper right this
might be a good exercise
worth knowing before you get
to um get to the hospital
setting and you guys will
all be in the hospital very
very soon right you might
be seeing a lot of different
patients you might need
to present you might not
have the computer in front of
you right you can just
quickly document um the lab
value in this in this order
uh so why is potassium
important uh potassium is
important because it's one of
the electrolytes that make
up the electrical gradient
in our body right uh the
precise movements of potassium
through the cell is important
for excitable tissues
that's appropriate for
cardiac conduction, cardiac
conduction, right, as well
as neuronal transmission,
and it allows for muscle
contractions, right.
So neuronal conditioning
and muscle contractions,
right, this is what
makes potassium, and it
has to be at a very
appropriate number, right,
maintaining balance inside
and outside of the cell.
It also acts as an acid
-based buffering for acute
acidity and alkylosis, right?
So when we have acidosis,
right, we're going to have
a lot of hydrogen ion that's
going to be outside the
cell, right? We're talking
about acidity, right? So
that's going to go inside the
cell, right, in exchange for
potassium coming out, right?
So they have the sodium,
the hydrogen-potassium
pump, So hydrogen is going to
come in, potassium is going
to go out, and that's going
to help buffer the acidotic
versus atherosclerosis
state that the body is in.
It's required for intracellular
glucose metabolism.
So your body needs
glucose for muscle and
for the brain to work,
and having potassium
will allow the metabolism
to happen, oxidative
phosphorylation and
protein synthesis.
There's a constant
cell concentration
that's critical for
enzyme activities.
Enzyme activities
within the body as
well as the cell
division and growth.
So we take potassium in every
day through the
food that we eat.
And most of the potassium gets
secreted through the kidneys.
So we're going to talk
later if somebody's going
to have kidney failure,
they're not going to
secrete the potassium
that they would normally
secrete. Now we're going
to have an issue where we
might have too much
potassium within the body.
When we take in the potassium,
it's going to get distributed
intracellular and
extracellular.
And again, most of
the potassium is
going to go inside
the cell and the
kidneys are going to
secrete 90% of it.
The GI tract will
be 10% and there's
other mechanisms to
get rid of potassium
that's very, very
less significant.
it. The World Health
Organization do recommend
3510 milligrams per day,
3,510 milligrams per day
for adults and for optimal
cardiovascular health.
Here's a whole bunch of
foods that do have potassium.
So you think about
all the different
types of foods, red
meat, vegetables,
pretty much known that it
has a lot of potassium.
It's really hard to
overdose some potassium
if you have somebody
with a normal kidney
function. But you might
have somebody with
kidney failure, you might
have to limit how much
potassium they take
in through their diet.
When we look at the
distribution of potassium, we
can see that most of the
potassium, I said this
again, it's intracellular.
Most of the potassium is
inside the cell, right,
while 10% is going to be
extracellular, right, 0
.4% in the plasma, right,
and this is where you're
going to get your potassium
level from, it's going to
be extracellular, right, but
most of the intracellular
potassium is going to be 90
% of all the potassium in the
body, and out of that, 76
% is going to be within the
muscle, right, So when we
talk about what kind of
symptoms that the patient is
going to have, right, muscle
weakness, fatigue, right,
these might play a role
in the type of symptoms
they have if they're
hyper or hypokalemic.
For these transcellular
potassium shifts, right,
there's a lot of different
factors that play a role in
either moving potassium
inside or outside the cell.
So we mentioned before acid
base, so if there's too
much hydrogen ion outside,
potassium is going to go
outside to let the hydrogen
ion come inside the cell.
Alkylosis would be just
the opposite, so you
want to maintain a balance,
so if there's very,
very little hydrogen ion
outside the cell, that's
going to allow the
hydrogen ion inside the
cell to go outside, and
the potassium outside is
going to come in through
the same pump and now
you are going to have a
lower potassium level.
Certain medications concern
pancreatic hormone, right,
insulin and glucagon are both
going to affect potassium
level, right, and when we
talk about insulin, insulin
is going to attach to a
receptor known as the sodium
potassium ATPase and what
that's going to do is
that's going to promote
potassium to go inside the cell,
right? So because that's
one of what it does,
insulin, right? It's going
to promote potassium to
go inside the cell,
right? Why not use it as a
treatment, right? It kind
of makes sense. That's
what it's going to do,
right? So if somebody comes
with hyperkalemia, we
can use insulin as a
treatment, which we're going
to talk about later on.
Hyperosmolarity, right?
Basically, water is going
to move outside of the cell,
and it's going to bring
potassium outside the cell,
right? and that's going
to be part of that solvent
drag effect and there's
other aldosterone is going
to have an effect on the
principal cell of the kidneys
so this is going to have
an effect on the kidneys
right that's going to be a
driving force for potassium
excretion right it's going
to get rid of potassium
and then exercise right
exercise we talk about muscle
use muscle breakdown cell
breakdown right that's
going to cause a transient
increase in in potassium
and I have another slide
on that specifically. Along
the distal tubal and
cloxin ducts, there's a net
secretion of potassium
which is stimulated by
aldosterone when there is
a dietary potassium excess.
So when you take in
too much potassium,
the body is going
to adjust and be
able to secrete the
extra potassium.
So the filtered potassium is
a GFR versus the time-desceram
Basically you're going
to have a passive
reabsorption in the
proximal convoluted tubule,
and then after that
you're going to have an
active secretion within
the collection ducts,
of the ducts by the principal
cells and Zicaliase cells.
So secretion and reabsorption
is increase or decrease
based on potassium,
concentration, and aldosterone.
So the body is going to
be able to adjust based
on how much potassium
you have within the body.
If you have too little
potassium, the body is not
going to get rid of all the
potassium. It's going to get
rid of less potassium, so
you can keep more potassium
within the body. So it's
going to maintain that
equilibrium, that balance
between too high and too low.
Again, most of the
potassium likes
to hang out inside of the cell,
and 10% of the
potassium is going to be
extracellular fluid, within
the extracellular fluid.
So what's going to be
disorders of potassium
metabolism can be classified
into different elements.
So you're going to
have altered intake,
meaning you might be
taking in too much or you
might be taking in
too little potassium.
You're going to have
altered elimination,
kidney failure is an
example, where you just
can't get rid of the
extra potassium. That's
going to be altered.
And then you're going to
have a deranged transcellular
potassium shift.
This is where too much
potassium is coming inside
the cell, leaving very
little outside the cell,
hypokalemia. Or you're
going to have a lot of
potassium coming outside of
the cell, like you're going
to have a lot of potassium
coming outside of
the cell because you're going
to have muscle breakdown,
you could have burn, you
could have eryptomyelitis,
different scenario
where the cell breaks
down, it's going to let
all the potassium come
outside, and now you're
going to have hyperkalemia.
Before, I did mention the
sodium-potassium ATPase pump.
Here's a good picture
right here and we have it
up there. And look at two
of the very, very common
medications that we've
seen or we've heard or we
know people that are on.
One of them being insulin.
Insulin is going to
promote cellular intake.
It's going to promotes
cellular intake, right,
potassium, cellular intake
of potassium, right,
shifting the potassium
from outside the cell
to inside the cell, right,
so when you have patients
come in, let's say they
have DKA or whatever
it might be, and you're
giving them insulin,
right, you got to make
sure you keep an eye
on the potassium level,
right, so that when
the potassium level
goes to a certain level,
you're able to supplement
it and give them
extra potassium that they need.
Beta-2 agonists,
right, think about the
albuterol, right, or even
epinephrine, right, again,
this is going to have
the same effect. It's
going to cause potassium to
go inside the cell, right?
So if it's going to cause
potassium to go inside
the cell, it might be a
good medication to use
if a patient comes in and
they are hypokalemius and
you have to treat them.
But you might have a patient
that's on an albuterol
inhaler and they're doing
it multiple time today
and now you look at the lab
and the potassium below,
right? So that might give
you an idea that it's
coming from the medication
as one of the effects.
So homeostasis mechanism
maintains plasma between
3.5 and 5, right?
Typically 3.5 and 5, right?
Don't get hung up if you're
looking at another resource
and maybe they say 5.5
or maybe they say 5.2.
it's in the vicinity
of about 5. So 3.5 and
5 is usually where the
body likes to keep the
potassium.
Now when we get a lab
value that's above 5,
right, that's where
we get the word hyper,
right, above kalemia,
right, so high potassium.
So somebody that has a
history of hyper or they have
a history of hypokalemia or
maybe you want to order and
just repeat the potassium
level, right, that might
be a good idea, a good time
to say, you know what, in
addition to rechecking the
potassium, I want to know
what the kidney function
is. I want to know what the
glucose level is. This might
be important if the patient
might be in DKA or they might
have some other hyperosmolar
state, creating the
potential for hyperkalemia.
You can check the urine for
electrolytes, potassium,
and caracinine.
You might even want to
consider doing an EKG,
being that hyperkalemia
and hypokalemia causes
EKG changes. You can
always check in EKD to
look for any effects
of potassium disorder.
So one of the more
common events in the very
beginning is you have
a sample error. And
when we talk about a
sample error, a lab is
only as good as the
specimen that you provide.
So we use the example that
you take the blood from a
patient and you notice that
the end cases are in the
bottom of the 13th inning
and now you want to watch the
game and you don't get the
blood to the lab in time.
So now you get hemolysis and
now you have a sample error.
That's why you always
want to examine the
patient and not just
look at the numbers
and make any decision
based on the numbers.
You also have potassium shift,
potassium coming
out of the cell.
You have decreased
excretion and you might
have excessive potassium
intake. More common
if you have a history
of kidney injuries or
kidney failure, excessive
potassium intake.
Or there might be other
reasons. For example, if
somebody goes to a doctor
and they get potassium,
then they go to
another doctor, another
specialist, and they're
also given potassium.
And then they go to
another specialist
and they're also
given potassium.
And now they might just be
taking way too much potassium.
So we talk about the
potassium shift, right? We
talk about potassium
coming outside of the cell,
right? So any activity
that break down the
cell is going to cause
the potassium to leak out,
right? So rhabdomyolysis,
right? An example I
always like to use is
that we get the elderly
patient, maybe they took
a fall and they don't have
the ability to get
back up and now they're
laying down on the kissing
floor for two to three
days before somebody
comes to check in on them.
So now that they're
laying down, they're
not moving, the muscle,
the breakdown is
going to cause an
increase in potassium.
Hemolysis, perhaps there
was a bad transfusion, the
patient got the wrong
type of blood or something
similar to that effect.
Now you're going to have
more cell breakdown, potassium
is going to come out.
Burn, breakdown of cells,
strenuous exercise,
again Then cell breakdown
leading to a leak in potassium.
Sepsis, cell breakdown
leading to high potassium.
Hypertinicity, right,
the water coming
outside of the cell,
right, and then you have
the solvent drag that
we mentioned before.
Insulin deficiency,
right, so you don't have
the insulin put in the
cell, potassium in, right,
so now the potassium
is going to be outside.
Acidotic, we talked about
before, right, that's with
the hydrogen ion, right, you
have too much of that. How
does the body maintain a
balance? It's going to want
the hydrogen ion to go inside
the cell which is going
to have an effect of the
potassium coming outside of
the cell in front of the
hydrogen-potassium problem.
Then there's certain medications
that can have an effect
that can cause the potassium
to come outside. right,
so digoxin is a good example.
What that does is that
actually that inhibits the
sodium potassium ATPase,
right.
So there's a lot of
different ways that the
potassium can come outside
of the cell and usually
that's through a shift.
We talked about exercise.
Exercise can have an
effect on potassium,
right, with the
muscle contracting.
Potassium is lost to the blood,
raising the blood potassium.
So we have the skeletal
muscle that loses
potassium during repetitive
action potential.
Skeletal muscle, we
mentioned 76% before, is a
major reservoir for potassium
in the body. Potassium
level may increase
markedly to around eight.
But conditioning will
reduce the increase in
potassium during exercise.
So that's why it's always
a good idea to do
conditioning, conditioning,
exercising, walking,
jogging, running,
keeping the body moving,
it has a better effect and
the ability to handle the
higher potassium and then
after exercise the muscle
regain lost potassium
through the sodium potassium
pump and normalization
of the potassium usually
within minutes with a
possibility for training
hypokalemia. So why this is
important is because somebody
might not be in the best
and out of shape and maybe
they have a history of
cardiac history, right,
they're going to be exposed
to a high potassium during
exercise, right, that
exposed to a major drop in
potassium after exercise
and that can cause an
impaired cardiac repolarization
and potentially cause
SCA or sudden cardiac death
or sudden cardiac arrest
and potentially some other
arrhythmia. arrhythmia.
So we have a decrease,
that's one way,
too much potassium
leaving the cell
outside the cell is going
to cause hypokalemia.
Now you're going to have
decreased excretion,
right, a good example
is somebody with kidney
failure or any other
kidney issues, right,
aldosterone has an effect on
the kidneys, right, itself,
so it's not too much of it
is going to cause kidneys
to be excreted by too
little hypo, too little
aldosterone is going to cause
potassium to go up because
you're not going to be
excreted as you normally would.
Some of these medications
that can also cause high
potassium is an H inhibitor
that is very, very
commonly used in patients
that have hypertension and
maybe they have a history
of renal issues and they're
also diabetic, ACE
inhibitors are used, and this
is over-the-counter as
well, NSAIDs, right, NSAIDs,
Motrin, Advil, Aleve,
Naproxen, Ibuprofen, these
all form in the class of
NSAIDs, right, and very, very
commonly used, but people
don't realize that it
can also have an effect on
potassium when they might
be taking too many, especially
if they're if they're
running and they're
exercising, now they're going
to have less, have an
effect on the kidneys. Now
the kidney might have a
little injury and now the
NSAID is going to increase
the potassium even more.
And then you can
also get it, we
talked about, excessive intake.
So hyperkalemia can be caused
due to an excessive intake.
But if you don't
have any kidney
issues, it's very,
very uncommon.
it's very very uncommon
it's not likely to happen if
you don't have any kidney
problems to get to be able
to take in too much potassium
unless maybe you ate
like 100 bananas but I
doubt anybody would do that
so unless you had any
kidney issues right then you
have to keep an eye on
how much potassium they're
taking in through their diet
and then I asked Progenic
I mentioned before you
go to one doctor you get
potassium you go to another
doctor you get potassium
and go to another doctor
and they give potassium and
now the patient don't realize
four different doctors
don't know that they're
giving the patient um
potassium while the other
doctors are as well and now
you're just taking way too
much potassium supplement.
Um the immediate danger of
hyperkalemia is the effect
that it has on the heart
right and that's why and
it's important that you wake
up at two in the morning
when the patient when
the nurse called you to
tell you that the potassium
is 6.2 but that's why we
get up and we go and evaluate
the patient. We don't
just go to bed and we
check the potassium in the
morning because you're going
to have immediate danger.
So you get out of bed as
painful as it might be
and you go and evaluate
the patient and determine
whether you need to do any
other workup or treatment.
Just because you
have no symptoms
does not include
severe hyperkalemia.
In more severe cases
where we talk about
the effect on the
muscles, weakness,
heart palpation,
extending paralysis,
parathesia, all very non
-specific symptoms but
they can be symptoms
related to hyperkalemia.
So history, find out the
history on the patient,
find out who's at risk for
high potassium. Those with
kidney disease, those who
are diabetic, those who
have heart failure, those
who have liver diseases.
You're going to do a
physical exam, and this is
all very non-specific. You
can have a normal exam.
You can have no physical
finding significant for
hyperkalemia, you can
have generalized weakness,
decrease deep tendon reflex, or
decrease the absence
in our valve sound.
The approach? Review the
patient's medication.
That's important. Review
all the medication
that the patient is
taking. They might go to a
primary and be given
an ACE inhibitor. They
go to their cardiologist
and be given an ARB.
And now they're on an
ACE inhibitor and an ARB.
And that's both for
their blood pressure, but
they're both going to be
increasing the potassium.
Find out what substance
is taken that might be
containing potassium, you
want to get that blood
pressure, you want
to assess for kidney
hypoperfusion, right, you
can check a kidney function.
So we're going to repeat
the potassium level,
we got to make sure we
have a true potassium
level that's high,
right, and then check the
kidneys, glucose, urine,
electrolytes that we
mentioned before and get
an EKG as well. So that's
3 in the morning call
that we mentioned before.
You're going to come down,
evaluate the patient,
and then you're going
to order additional
labs. You want to order
the three pieces of
potassium and have it
done ASAP and then get the
kidney function, glucose,
electrolytes, EKG.
The approach to hyperkalemia,
EKG should be considered
if their potassium is
greater than 6. If they're
symptomatic or they
have high risk, they
have a history of kidney
issues, you might even
lower that number to 5.5.
You're not going to
go wrong ordering EKG,
but you want to make
sure you're getting
an EKG, you're looking
for EKG changes.
You're going to be looking
for symptoms of EKG,
rapid onset of hyperkalemia,
is not a great thing to
have, so you can't go from
a normal 3.5 potassium,
all of a sudden to be
a 5.8, 5.9, 6.0, right?
That's a rapid onset. If
it's quick, that body might
not be able to adjust as
well. And you want to look
at underlying kidney
disease, heart disease, and
osteosis, liver issues
for cases of hypercolemia.
EKG changes, right? You're
looking at peak T wave,
right? Generally the earliest
sign, right, so peak T
waves are generally the
earliest signs of hyperkalemia,
right, you're going to
get P wave flattening, PR
interval, prolongation,
widening of the QRS, right,
hyperkalemia-induced arrhythmias,
right, not a great thing,
VTAC, VFib, and, and, um,
a systole, so things can
get pretty, things can move
along pretty quick, right,
that's why you're not
waiting for the morning to
take a look at the patient,
you're going to do this
right away, get the EKG,
and you're going to be
looking for these EKG changes
all right so again we're
looking for the P wave
flattening uh the peak T wave
uh the peak T wave um the
P wave flattening uh the
PR prolongation the QRS
widening and um and then
eventually if things don't
get so good right this is
hopefully by then if you're
a resident or an intern,
you called your attending,
you get cardiology on
board, and then hopefully
you had all the treatment
that we're going to talk
about in just a little bit.
Oh, we're going to
talk about that now.
Treatment for hyperkalemia,
ultimately you're
going to find the
cause and correct the
cause for compensating
for its long-term goal.
So that's the long
-term goal, it's to find
the cause, but you might
not have time because
EKG changes are
happening very quickly,
right? So you're going
to go to rapid treatment,
right? Rapid treatment,
you're going to give them
everything you got to try
to get that potassium lower,
right? If hyperkalemia is
suggested, you're not going
to delay treatment to find
out what the cause is.
The goal is we want
to prevent life
-threatening cardiac
conduction. Cardiac
conduction, very,
very important.
Prevent neuromuscular
disturbances, and you want
to shift that potassium
into the cell, lower
the potassium level. You
want to eliminate the
excess potassium, again
lower the potassium level,
and you want to
resolve the underlying
disturbance, right, which is
going to make that potassium
less likely to be
increased in the future.
Um, indication for
prompt treatment,
right, um, symptoms
of hyperkalemia,
uh, changes of
EKG, right, severe
hyperkalemia 6.5, you
repeat the potassium, it
was 6.2, you just
repeated it, now 6.5.
You're going to want to
begin the treatment options.
Rapid onset of
hyperkalemia, heart disease
again, liver and kidney
disease. Underline,
they're going to
put them at a higher
risk of having an
effect of hyperkalemia.
So here's a slide I had
most of the treatment.
We're going to go through this
in a little bit more detail.
So the calcium, IV
calcium, it's not really
going to have an effect
on the potassium level,
so no effect on the
potassium level, but it's
going to stabilize the
cardiac muscle membrane.
So what happens is the
calcium is going to raise
the action potential
threshold, and it's going
to reduce excitability,
and that's going to cause
the heart to have a less
chance of a significant
event happening because
of that difference.
Insulin and glucose.
You don't want to just
give insulin because it's
going to lower your
glucose level. So you've
got to make sure you give
them the glucose, the
dextrose, so that you
maintain that equilibrium.
That's going to put the
potassium back inside
the cell. So it's going
to have no total effect
on the total body
potassium. it's just going
to put the potassium
back inside the cell.
Albuterol, beta agonics put
the body, put the potassium
inside the cell. Again,
no effect on the total
potassium, right? So you
still have the potassium
in your body, but it's
going to be inside the cell.
Sodium bicarb should
not be used in a
monotherapy, and
usually that's great
for a patient that
may have metabolic
acidosis.
And if the patient has
a history of kidney
failure, right, you might
even need to get hemodialysis
and what that's going
to do is that is going
to take the potassium
away from the body and
then again just a reminder
right you're giving the
insulin right just keep an
eye on the glucose level
right if the glucose is over
250 right you're going to
give the insulin alone and
then if it goes below 250
then you're going to want
to have to supplement
additional glucose so your
body don't go into hypoglycemia
which is too low sugar
too low of a sugar level
So IV calcium, right? So
IV calcium is what we just
mentioned before, right?
So this is where Cookie
Monster is going to play
a role, right? We're going
to pretend that the jar
is going to be the blood
vessel or the body and
the cookies are going to
be the K, right? So the K
is right here, right? K,
K,
right? So potassium is
going to be the cookies,
right? So when you have too
much cookies in the blood
vessel in the body right
um you can't eat a lot of
cookies without having any
milk right so when you have
a lot of cookies you're
going to want to have milk
along with it right so
you're going to have milk
and that's going to create
a balance right cookies
and milk right you're not
going to just going to drink
milk alone you're not
going to just drink eat
cookies alone right you're
going to make a balance
between cookies and milk and
that's going to stabilize
the cardiac muscle cell
membrane again no effect on
the potassium. It's not
going to put potassium
inside or outside the cell.
It's just going to prevent
a cardiac issue, conduction
issues from occurring.
All right, so I put
these pictures in here.
So just try not to
try to use it only for
educational purposes. A
few years back, somebody
decided to make it
into a meme. So we
always find out. Somebody
always let us know.
So,
but good sense of
humor, good meme.
Inhaled beta agonists and
insulin, right? So this
is going to be insulin
again with dextrose, sugar.
When you have too many
cookies in the jar,
when you have too many
cookies inside the
blood vessel, what
are you going to do is
you're going to want to
put it into the cell,
right? So you're going
to put it into the
cell and that's
going to lower the
extracellular potassium,
and that's going to
have no effect on the
total body potassium.
So again, you're shifting
the potassium inside
the cell, right? And
you do that with a beta
agonist, with abutyl,
and with insulin, right?
So you have too many
cookies inside the
jar, in the blood, now
you put it into a small
bag, and that is
going to be a way to
lower your potassium
level extracellular.
by putting it in
your cellulite.
So in summary, right, you're
not going to lose any cookies,
right, you're just displacing
them for maybe you're
going to have them later
as a midnight snack.
So you're still
going to have it,
it's just not going
to be in the jar.
It's going to be in
the bag, in the cell.
Then when you have too many
cookies and the kidneys
are not working, right,
another way to get rid of the
potassium is you're going
to have to get rid of it
from the body. not put it
inside the cell, but you're
going to get it out of the
body. How do you get it
out of the body? You get that
done through hemodialysis,
removal of the potassium
from the body, and that's
the method of choice for
those with kidney failure.
So that's really
giving the cookies to
the trash can, to
this guy over here,
and eliminate the
potassium altogether
by directly taking
it out of the blood.
To exhalate, there are
some other medications
that are out there
that exchanges,
that goes through
the GI tract and
increases the fecal
excretion of potassium.
So basically this lowers
your total body of
potassium, it gets it
outside of the body.
But the problem with
these medications is that
they can have GI issues
and that causes the U.S.
Food and Drug
Administration to have a box
warning that there could
be GI complications.
So it's to be avoided
in any patient that
has an abnormal bowel
function or anybody
that might be post-op
or those with any kind
of bowel issue,
inflammatory bowel disease.
So hyperkalemia, and again
with these medications,
the other thing you want to
keep in mind is don't give
it with other medications
right the FDA said three
hours before and after right
would you take any other
medications that you might
be taking and basically
it's going to bind the
potassium and exchange for
sodium lower the body total
potassium a big time GI
complications right FDA
warning right so just make
sure they don't have any other
any GI issues and um they
don't have any abnormal
bowel function again
inflammatory bowel disease
IBS or whatever else might be
occurring. And then
there's additional
treatment. There's the
GI cation exchanger.
Pateromare is one of
the more common name
out there. This was
released in 2015.
It's not for life-threatening
hyperkalemia, so you're
not going to begin this at
3 in the morning for that
patient that we talked
about. But this is for somebody
that might have a chronic
elevated potassium that
have a history of chronic
kidney disease, right,
and maybe they have other
comorbidity issues such as
diabetes, heart failure,
that put them at a higher
risk, right. And, again,
that's going to increase
fecal potassium excretion
by binding the potassium in
the lumen of the GI tract.
Some other medication
that's there is
porosomide, renal
secretion of the potassium,
right. So renal secretion
of the potassium,
meaning the LASIK
is going to have an
effect on the kidneys
that's going to help
the kidney get rid
of more potassium.
The effect is dependent
on urine output. So
you have to have good
urine. You have to be
at least uvolemic for
it to occur correctly.
You want to use in caution
for anybody that might
not have fluid or there
might be fluid depleted
or hypovolemic or any
kind of renal impairment.
Again, LASIK is used
for other medical
conditions, right, so you
might have one drug that
can have multiple
benefits for the patient.
So we're going to bring
Cookie Monster back, and we
talked about the K-Excalate,
Petromia, right, Locoma,
right, there's some other
brain names that are out
there, I'm not going to list
every one of them for you,
but just know that these
are occurred through the GI
tract, so instead when you
have a lot of potassium,
right, You're going to
eat the cookies, right?
You're not getting rid of
it. You're not putting it
inside the cell, right?
You're just going to put
it through the GI tract,
right? So when you have
too many cookies, you can
take K-exalate to help
potassium get eliminated
through the GI tract.
You can do this in front
of the TV or you can
do it at home, right,
for non-life-threatening
conditions. But just
be careful that if
you do this, you might
get a bellyache, right?
Bellyache meaning associated GI
complications, right? So
given orally, rectally,
actually could be
given rectally.
It's a non-renal
elimination, right?
We talked about the
renal elimination,
right?
LASIK, but this is a
non-renal elimination,
and it lowers the total
body of potassium.
Thank
Cookie Monster for being
part of the lecture, right?
So here's a shot
that's trying to
summarize everything
we just said, calcium
gluconate versus
calcium chloride,
right? So IV, most of the
time, we're going to be using
calcium gluconate. I don't
expect you to know the
difference between gluconate
or chloride, but in the
hospital, you might know that
gluconate was usually IV,
but chloride, you'll probably
not do it through the
IV. You'll probably do it
more through the central IV.
Insulin, right? Again,
insulin, if you're
going to give them
dextrose, you're going
to shift the potassium
inside the cell.
Albutyl, sodium bicarb,
kayexylate, LASIK,
and hemodialysis.
Another diagram, algorithm,
sodium potassium less than
6 and they're not symptomatic.
You might give them
another medication to remove
the potassium in a subacute
setting. but if they're
over six and or they have
EKG changes, right, you're
going to initiate calcium,
you're going to
initiate insulin and
albuterol, right, maybe
vicarb if you might
think they have a
metabolic acidosis.
And the goal is just
to get rid of the
potassium, right. So you
might not begin the K
-exalate right away,
but it's definitely in
your potential to
prescribe at some point. I
counsel the patient,
reduce dietary potassium,
right? So if you're
eating too much potassium,
tell them to eat a
little less potassium,
right? You may need to
make some adjustments
in medications, right?
Maybe they don't, maybe
being on an ACE inhibitor
or an ORB, their
potassium is elevated,
right? You might change it
over to a different blood
pressure medication.
Or if they have good kidney
function, right? Maybe
you can add the diuretic,
right? Maybe you can add
the diuretic that can help
secrete extra potassium.
Avoiding NSAID, right?
again, NSAID has the effect
where it's going to increase
the potassium, and then
adding the diuretic, which
we just mentioned over
here, if the patient has
sufficient renal function.
And we're going to go into
hypokalemia, right? So
hypokalemia is anything
below 3.5. We talked about 3
.5 to 5, right? Anything
below 3.5, and the etiology
is going to be just the
opposite of everything we
just talked about, right?
It's going to have a decreased
intake. You're not taking
in enough potassium,
you're going to have too
much potassium loss through
the kidneys. You're going
to have potassium going
inside the cell, right,
and you're going to have a
decreased potassium intake
typically coupled with another
cause, and an exterrenal
potassium loss, right,
maybe they're losing
through a GI tract, right,
exterrenal, meaning outside
the kidneys, potassium loss,
or you can have another
example of a sample error.
All right, so an increased
aldosterone effects,
right, so a patient that
has hyperaldosteronism,
right, there's a
lot of different
genetic disorders, a lot
of different diseases,
a lot of different
conditions, right, that
can cause to have an
increased aldosterone
effect, right, and
now you're going
to be excruing too
much of the potassium.
Increased flow at the
distal nephron, so
you're going to be
thinking about your LASIK,
even thinking about
the thiazide diuretic.
Hypomagnesium, this is
going to get you some extra
points on the rotation.
When you're giving somebody
potassium and the potassium's
not going up, you're
going to consider that
maybe they have a magnesium
deficiency, which is a
very common occurrence with
hypokalemia. For many
disorders of the distal nephron
may cause both potassium
and magnesium wasting.
And the other
thing, low magnesium
inhibits the sodium-potassium
ATPase activity,
right? So it's not
going to allow that
potassium to, it's
not going to allow the
influx of the potassium
inside the cell,
right? So when that happens,
when that gets inhibited,
right, you're going to
have a low potassium,
you're going to have a low
magnesium that goes along
with it, right? That's
going to be exaggerated.
And then some genetic disorder,
I'm not going to
question you on all these
specific conditions, but
just know that there's a
lot of conditions that
are out there, and you're
going to get to them at
some point when you get
to your genetic lecture,
your kidney lecture.
So etiology, potassium shift
inside the cell, so you
have too much insulin,
that's going to push all that
extra potassium inside the
cell, so post-prandial or
iatrogenic towards, right
maybe somebody overdosed on
insulin by accident um like
after a meal you take too much
insulin too much medication
um alkalosis is going to
be just the opposite of
acidosis right so alkalosis
is you're going to have too
much hydrogen ion um whoop
you're going to have too
little hydrogen ion you're
going to have too little
hydrogen ion outside the body
that you're going to hydrogen
ion is going to want to
go outside to maintain
equilibrium so when hydrogen an
iron go outside, you're
going to have K that's going
to go inside, right, and
that's going to create a low
potassium outside the cell,
right, hypokalemia, right,
too much of a beta agonist, and
then there's some
kidney issues,
hypokalemia, I'm not
kidding, a thyroid
condition that can also
lead to, or thyroid
disorder that can
lead to hypokalemia.
Etiology It can also
be exterinal, exterinal
meaning outside the cell,
vomiting and or diarrhea,
villus adenoma,
Zollinger-Ellison syndrome.
Again, I'm not going to
test you on these specifically,
but Zollinger-Ellison
syndrome is a gastrin
-secreting tumor of the pancreas
that's going to stimulate
acid-secreting cells
and that's going to lead to
potassium being depleted.
Symptoms are going
to be very, very
non-specific. You
might have no symptoms.
You might have a
lot of symptoms.
Because potassium is
intracellular, it's like
to hang out mostly in the
muscles, muscle cramps,
fatigue, weakness, you
may get constipation.
You might have a
history of paralysis,
maybe thyroid issue, or use of
insulin or beta
agonist in the history.
Physical exam, blood
pressure can be high, blood
pressure can be low,
depending on what cause in the
hypokalemia and what other
conditions that they have.
So if they have too
much aldosterone effect,
the blood pressure
might be high. But if
they have too much of
the diuretic effect,
the blood pressure
might be low.
So again, it's
very non-specific,
irregular heart rate,
paralysis, and decreased bowel
Diagnosis is going to be
made once you come out
with the potassium and
you're going to order
additional blood work.
We mentioned before,
you're going to order
kidney function. You're
going to want to know
what the glucose is. We're
what the magnesium is.
In EKG, you can get
an ABG if there's any
acute setting, in
the hospital setting,
or you can get a 24
-hour urine potassium.
hypokalemia, EKG changes,
decreased T-wave amplitude.
This is going to be the
first EKG manifestation
of hypokalemia. So
decreased T-wave amplitude,
decreased T-wave amplitude
is going to be the first
EKG manifestation of
hypokalemia. And that's going
to further progress as
it gets more severe. It's
going to turn into ST
interval depressant, T-wave
inversion, PR interval
prolongation and arrhythmias.
Again, EKGs, changes,
it's going to progress
as you go through.
You're going to
notice the decrease in
the T-wave amplitude.
Urine analysis. You're
looking to see if it's an
extra renal or a renal
cause. So if you do a 24-hour
urine and you're coming out
to be potassium is greater
than 30 millimole, that's
going to be, okay, It's
coming from the kidney,
right, as a renal cause.
You might have a urine
potassium to carotidine
ratio that might be
higher than 13, right,
and that also comes
from renal wasting,
right, or you could
have a trans-tubular
potassium gradient,
right, not very commonly
ordered in the primary
care setting, right, and
basically it's an index
reflecting the conserving
of potassium, right,
within the kidneys.
Here's an algorithm to
help for the patient with
hypokalemia. I don't
expect you to know every
condition on this slide,
but just know that there's
a lot of different
conditions, and you may want
to look at the thyroid.
Is it hypo versus hypo?
Are there genetic
conditions that
might be playing a role in it?
I might be taking
too many diuretics.
The diarrhea, acidotic,
high potassium
excreasing, metabolic acid-base
abnormality, acidosis
versus akalosis.
So, a lot of different
things can cause potassium to
be low, just know how to
find it, how to diagnose
it, and what conditions
they may be associated with.
This is more if you're thinking
of a genetic component.
I put this up just for
the completion of the
lecture. Again, I'm not going
to ask you any questions
on it, anything similar
to it, but just know that
there's different conditions
relating to the thyroid.
Candidate for
potassium replacement,
anybody that might
be low in potassium,
anybody unable or
unwilling to eat a low
sodium diet, a patient
who has nausea,
vomiting, diarrhea,
extra renal excretion,
or a patient unable to
stop a diuretic, they have
to be on a diuretic, they
have to be on a laxative,
you want to give them
potassium, and a patient
who has drug-related
potassium. Maybe they're on
a diuretic or LASIK for
other medical conditions,
but now there's going to
be hypokalemia. Now you're
going to want to supplement
their potassium level.
Prevention of potentially
life-threatening
cardiac conduction. So
just like we said, too much
potassium is bad for
the body. Too little
potassium is bad for the
body. And you want to make
sure you raise the
potassium to a lower level.
You want to raise
the potassium to a
safe level, right?
You want to make sure
that you get it to
a nice, safe level.
And then again, you're
going to pinpoint
on rotation, right?
Potassium is not going
off, you keep
supplementing potassium,
right? Check the magnesium,
right? Again, magnesium
is going to inhibit the
effect of the sodium
potassium ATPase, right? And
that's going to reduce the
the influx of potassium
inside the muscle cell,
and that's going to have
an effect on the excretion
of the potassium out of the
body through the kidneys,
because now you're going
to have higher potassium
outside the cell, the
kidney is going to secrete
it, and you're going to
end up with hypokalemia.
uh determining the approximate
potassium deficit right
so serum potassium drops
about 0.3 milliequivalent
per liter for every 100
milliequivalent reduction in
total body of potassium
and that's just because of
the way potassium like to
hang out inside of the cell
most of the potassium hangs
out inside of the cell to
treat it get a good
history get a good medical
history have the patient
bring in the whole bag of
medication that they're
bringing that they're taking
on a daily basis, right,
and take a look at one
by one of every medication
that they're taking.
If it's associated
with a diuretic, that
will reduce the strength
of the diuretic.
If there's a comorbid
condition, take advantage of
it, right, so if they have
a history of high blood
pressure and they have low
potassium, right, maybe put
them on an ACE inhibitor so
we know that ACE inhibitor
is going to raise the
potassium level. Or maybe just
put them on a beta blocker,
right, because just like
a beta agonist, it's
going to be lowering the
potassium level. A beta blocker
is going to be increasing
the potassium level. And
then a potassium sparing
diuretic would be beneficial
as well if they have any
other medical conditions
that might warrant its use.
Increased dietary
potassium, right? Something
as simple as eating an
extra banana every day.
Low normal versus mild
hypokalemia, especially
in patients that have a
hypertension and heart
disease, the effects
may be limited. Most of
the potassium in food
coupled with phosphate.
Most cases of hypokalemia
involve chloride
depletion and would
respond to potassium
chloride, which is
prescribed in a prescription.
IV potassium. Just remember
that IV potassium can
hurt. It hurts. It
definitely hurts patients, So
if you can do potassium
by mouth, that's probably
the ideal thing, but
there's going to be
circumstances where, you
know what, they're critically
ill and they need to get
potassium through an IV,
right? Or maybe they can't
tolerate anything by mouth.
So increased risk of
hypokalemia with IV potassium.
They're going to have pain.
They're going to feel it.
And it's used in severe
hypokalemia or hypokalemia
with EKG changes or symptoms
relating to hypokalemia or
the patient unable to tolerate
PL or oral medication.
Cardiac monitoring should
not be given in a dextrose
-containing solution
unless you're giving the
patient dextrose to treat
anything else, right, for
another medical condition.
Now, if you're giving them
dextrose, then you can
give the potassium with it.
But usually potassium
is given as a bolus.
It's never given as
a bolus. It's usually
given with normal saline.
So again, IV potassium
is given through any
other IV fluid and it's
never given as a bolus.
That could be very,
very significantly
harmful for the patient.
And more commonly,
it's going to be given
through normal saline,
but if needed to, it can
also be given through
a dextrose solution.
We talk about hot oral
potassium, non-urgent, right,
you can prescribe this
medication used in the
prevention of hypokalemia
in a patient that has a
persistent loss, a patient
might be on diuretic therapy
or maybe they have a
condition that's hyper
-adoptimalism, right, you're
going to give them potassium
supplement oral, which
is a better way to, um,
the patient for
them to tolerate it.
Going back to the cookie
jar, right, now we have the
cookie jar, but we have so
little cookies, we have so
little K, right, how do we
fix it? We fix it by putting
in potassium, putting in
cookies in the cookie jar.
So when you have two
little cookies in the
cookie jar, you're going
to need to add more.
You can run through a
PO or through an IV.
And if you need to
remember that, just
know that it's more
fun to eat the cookies
than it is to get a
cookie through an IV,
right, so that's why if
you can do PL, go PL,
increase the potassium in the
diet, increase
through supplement,
and increase through an
IV, given through with
normal saline, but if
needed to, you can also
give it through a dextrose
-containing solution.
Emergency situation, right,
you're going to be in
a hospital, you're going
to check potassium every
one to two hours. In the
stable condition, you can
check every four to six
hours and as an outpatient
setting you could check
weekly right then you
could check monthly and
you could check quarterly
right if everything's
stable you can check it
eventually quarterly or if
you need to every six months
uh summary slide um
interpretation of potassium
abnormal potassium right so
knowing that it's too high
or too low is not a good
thing right so you want to
make the equilibrium and
going back to the introduction
slide right so you get that
call at two or three in
the morning, right, you're
very tired. This is the
one lab where you definitely
do want to get up. You want
to get out of bed and you
want to go evaluate the,
evaluate the patient, right.
And they're going
to be calling you.
The nurses are told
to call the intern
before they wake
up the attending,
right. If you need help,
obviously the senior vigilants
are there for you, right.
The attending physicians
But this is something you
just got to know how to triage.
And something like this,
right, you want to make
sure that this is more of a
critical issue to be dealing
with, and you want to make
sure you address this right
away, right? If somebody
called you to tell you the
triglyceride is 158, which
is a little bit elevated,
right? Triglyceride or the
LDL or whatever it might
be, right? You don't have to
get up at 3 in the morning
to go check on the patient.
Potassium, definitely get
up, evaluate the patient.
Diagnosis and treatment
of hypo and hyperkalemia.
Identify a key finding
on an EKG, right, when
the potassium is too high
or too low, right, so
you might see that at
some point, EKG finding
associated with hyper
and hypokalemia, and know
the treatment and treat
the underlying cause.
So, a reference slide,
definitely leave feedback,
I appreciate you all
listening to the lecture, I
know it went a few minutes
over, but I hope Cookie
Monster was a little bit
of a help to help you
remember the different
ways to treat hyper and
hypokalemia. If you all have
any questions for me, please
reach out. Otherwise,
thank you for your time,
and I will see you on
campus at some point. Have a
great evening or morning,
and I'll see you soon.